"Diet and Caloric Restriction for Longevity—
The Monkey Trials"
Calorie restriction
in primates to extend lifespan.
Will it work?
There's only one way
to find out.
There have been
four investigations
of calorie restriction and
lifespan in nonhuman primates.
The first was published in 2003,
an analysis of the mortality
of 117 rhesus monkeys
followed for about 25 years
in a lab,
eight of whom had their
Purina monkey chow restricted.
The average survival
of the restricted monkeys
was to 32 years of age,
compared to 25 years
for the control monkeys.
However, it was more of
an observational study,
since the monkeys weren't
randomly assigned,
and although in the abstract
they talk about
the survival advantage
and how the ad libitum monkeys,
the eat-all-you-want monkeys,
had more than twice
the risk of death,
they acknowledge
deeper in the paper
that the difference in death
did not reach
statistical significance,
meaning it may very well
have been a fluke.
That was all we had, though,
until results
started trickling in
from the famous pair of studies
that involved randomizing
about 200 rhesus monkeys
to caloric restriction
or more normal diets,
one out of the University
of Wisconsin-Madison
and another from the
National Institute of Aging.
The UW study reported a 30
percent caloric restriction
significantly delayed disease
and improved survival,
but the NIA study did not.
In the UW study,
caloric restriction
reduced the incidence
of age-related diseases
including cancer,
cardiovascular disease,
brain atrophy,
and muscle wasting,
preserving muscle mass,
demonstrating caloric
restriction can delay aging,
but in the NIA study,
the difference
in age-related diseases
did not achieve
statistical significance.
In the UW study,
the restricted monkeys lived
to an average of about 29 years
compared to the control monkeys,
who lived closer to the average
for monkeys in captivity
of about 26 years old.
In contrast, though one
of the restricted monkeys
in the NIA study became
the longevity record holder
for the species at age 43,
on average, the restricted group
didn't live any longer
than the control animals.
Why the disparate results
between the two studies?
In the NIA study that found no
significant lifespan difference,
the control group
was not fed ad libitum,
but rather had food
portioned out to prevent
excessive weight gain.
In contrast,
in the UW study,
the control monkeys could eat
as much as they wanted
throughout the day
so ended up weighing more
than the NIA control animals.
Of course caloric restriction
would improve
the health and survival
of overweight monkeys
just as weight loss
would be beneficial
for overweight people,
but the null results
in the NIA study suggest
that normal weight people
might not benefit
from restricting further.
The NIA monkeys were also fed
a healthier diet.
The diet in the UW study
where they saw significant
benefit to cutting down
was an ultra-processed
concoction of largely
milk protein, corn oil,
corn starch, and table sugar,
whereas the NIA diet actually
included unprocessed plant foods
such as corn,
soybeans, and wheat,
and so actually had
some phytonutrients.
About 29 percent of the UW diet
was straight sugar,
compared to 4 percent
in the NIA diet.
American adults get about
17 teaspoons of sugar a day,
which is about
13 percent of calories.
The contrasting findings suggest
that the worse your diet is,
the more important it is
to eat less of it.
The fourth study
was on grey mouse lemurs,
among the smallest of primates,
standing just three inches tall.
Those randomized to
a 30 percent caloric restriction
compared to an ad libitum
control group
lived a whopping
50 percent longer.
And not just average lifespan,
but maximal lifespan.
The maximum lifespan was boosted
by about 20 percent.
However,
the "calorie restricted" group
still weighed heavier
than their wild counterparts,
so again this may just be
an illustration
of the harms of obesity
and another indictment against
all-you-can-eat buffets.
Also, those in the calorie
restriction group experienced
an acceleration of age-related
loss of grey matter
throughout their brains,
though this did not appear
to translate into cognitive
or behavioral differences.
Pooling the three rhesus monkey
studies together,
there seemed to be
lower age-related mortality
but no significant difference
in average lifespans overall
between the caloric
restriction groups
and the control groups.
Given the time and expense,
there is little chance
we are going to see any more
long-term primate studies
on caloric restriction
for life extension.
So what can we draw
from the primate data to date?
If you're overweight
or living off junk food,
eating less is a good idea.